Often when they talk about Performance
часто Коли говорять про Performance
websites talk about Performance
веб-сайти говорять про Performance
frontend backend First meaningle Pain and
фронтенду бекенда First meaningle Pain і
so on but we have another huge
так далі але є у нас інша величезна
problem that limits us and limits
проблема яка нас обмежує і обмежує
performance greatly or let's say more
сильно перформанс або скажімо більш
July it will be more correct our
липеньці це буде правильніше наши
websites and it is the speed of light and it
веб-сайти і це швидкість світла і
seems the speed of light is not so small and It would
здається швидкість світла не така мала і
seem what is so here but
Здавалося б Чого ж тут такого але
let's calculate it now and see
давайте зараз це порахуємо і побачимо
how much
наскільки
the speed of light is a problem for us and
швидкість світла є для нас проблемою і
why we do not allow it enough We have
чому її недостатньо припустимо У нас є
our backend somewhere and it is located in
десь бекенд наш і він знаходиться в
San Francisco somewhere California or in
сан-франциско десь Каліфорнії або в
Los Angeles it does not matter in principle
лос-анджелесі неважливо в принципі
the distance plus or minus is the same if we take
відстань плюс-мінус однакова якщо брати
from Kyiv and our backend processes the request
з Києва і наш бекенд відпрацьовує запит
in let it be 20 milliseconds that is 20
за нехай це буде 20 мілісекунд тобто 20
milliseconds the backend processes the request
мілісекунд бекенд відпрацьовує запит
now we have the next question we will now
тепер у нас наступне питання ми зараз
calculate the theoretical then we will check
порахуємо теоретичне потім перевіримо на
all this in practice but what interests us is how
практиці все це але що нас цікавить за
long it will take us to get an answer from
скільки ми зможемо отримати відповідь з
our backend if our client or
нашого бекенда якщо наш клієнт чи
browser is located in Kyiv so that Kent in
браузер знаходиться в Києві аби Кент в
Los Angeles the
лос-анджелесі
first thing we are interested in is the distance from
перше що нас цікавить - це відстань від
Kyiv to Los Angeles and from Kyiv to
Києва до лос-анджелеса і від Києва до
Los Angeles we have approximately and the same
лос-анджелеса у нас приблизно і так само
to San Francisco approximately 10 thousand
до сан-франциско приблизно 10 тисяч
kilometers and now let's make a
кілометрів а тепер Давайте зробимо
very very optimistic second assumption
дуже-дуже оптимістичне друге припущення
and the following assumption that our computer
і припущення наступне що наш комп'ютер
which is in Kyiv let's assume there is
який знаходиться в Києві припустимо там
a laptop
лептоп
connected by a direct fiber optic cable
під'єднаний оптоволокном прямим от
one end is inserted into our laptop and the
вставлений один кінець в наш ноутбук а
other end is inserted into a server in
другий кінець вставлений в сервер в
San Francisco or Los Angeles that is
сан-франциско чи в лос-анджелесі тобто і
this cable is 10,000 km long and where it is purely
цей кабель довжиною 10 000 км і де чисто
in a straight line we don't have wi-fi we don't have
по прямій у нас немає wi-fi у нас немає
any routing there there are no
ніякої там маршрутизації немає ніяких
providers there is nothing we don't have that's
провайдерів нічого немає у нас немає от
why we are not going in a straight line yes somewhere somehow there
що ми йдемо не по прямій да десь якось
the cable is laid No we have a cable
там кабель прокладений Ні у нас кабель
exclusively
виключно
straight from point A to point B the shortest
прямий з точки А в точку б найкоротший
route that is these 10,000 km and we know
маршрутом тобто ці 10 000 км і ми знаємо
that our speed of light in a vacuum is 300
що в нас швидкість світла в вакуумі 300
thousand kilometers per second If we
тисяч кілометрів на секунду Якщо ми
Let's take the speed of light in fiber optics,
візьмемо швидкість світла в оптоволокні
it will be approximately 200 thousand
вона приблизно буде 200 тисяч
200 thousand kilometers per second, that is,
200 тисяч кілометрів на секунду тобто на
a third less, but still, these
третину менше але все одно ніби оці
numbers seem quite high. Let's now
цифри досить високі давайте тепер
calculate what we got, that is, in order for
порахуємо що у нас вийшло тобто для того
light to travel 10,000 km at
щоб пройти 10 000 км світло при
a speed of 200 thousand kilometers per
швидкості в 200 тисяч кілометрів на
second, it will take
секунду знадобиться
50 milliseconds, that is, what can we say
50 мілісекунд тобто що ми можемо сказати
that there and back if the ping worked in
що туди і назад якби пінг відпрацює за
100 milliseconds under these ideal conditions,
100 мілісекунд при цих ідеальних умовах
which cannot exist in principle at all.
які взагалі не можуть існувати в
That is, we will never play there
принципі Тобто ми ніколи не пограємо там
with friends. I don't know any cs:go that
з друзями Я не знаю якісь cs:go які
are in the States with a ping of less than 100
знаходяться в Штатах з пінгом менше 100
milliseconds. Because the
мл секунд Тому що нас
speed of light will not allow us to do this.
нам не дозволить це зробити швидкість
Let's try to
світла Давайте спробуємо зараз трішечки
draw a little diagram on your form.
помалювати діаграмок в бланк твій милі
I drew a small diagram and we see that
малював невелику діаграму і ми бачимо
the request from Kyiv to Ellie takes 50 milliseconds.
запит від Києва до Еллі займає 50 млсенд
Then we process our year quest 20
потім ми процесимо наш рік квест 20
milliseconds and return the respondent another 50 million
млсенд і повертаємо ріспондент ще 50 млн
and that's all we need together.  120
і того у нас все разом займає 120
milliseconds, that is, the time to receive a
мілісекунд тобто час на отримання
response is 6 times longer than
відповіді в 6 разів довший більше ніж
the time to process our request on the backend,
час на обробку нашого запиту на бекенді
but that's not all. Because we
але це насправді не все Тому що ми
make a request via TCP and we also have TCP
робимо запит по tcp і у нас є ще tcp
handshake, what is TCPEEC - this is when we
хенд-шик що таке tcpeec - це коли ми
establish a connection with the server and
встановлюємо з'єднання з сервером і в
we first have the first year of Quest 7 from the
нас спочатку йде перший рік квест 7 від
client to the server, then back 7EK and
клієнта до сервера потім назад 7ek і
then EK with different flash drives to
потім екс з різними цими флашками для
establish a connection in UDP, there is
того щоб встановити з'єднання в udp
no such thing in TCP, and due to this,
такого немає в tcpe і за рахунок цього
we have certain guarantees there and TCP is more
там у нас є певні гарантії і tcp більш
reliable than UDP, let's also add this to
надійні ніж udp давайте це теж додамо в
our diagram, that is, from Kyiv to Aley, we
нашу діаграму тобто з Києва в Алей ми
first connect Sin 50
робимо спочатку приз'єднанні Сін 50
milliseconds, then we will do it at the end,
мілісекунд потім ми зробимо в кінці
and here we have
а тут у нас
the opposite with Life Kyiv, it
навпаки з Лайф Київ
will also be
теж буде
7 EK, this is our TCP Hand
7 Ек це наш tcp Hand
Shake. Well, what we have is
Shake Добре що ми маємо ми маємо
quite good. What does it look like
діаграму досить непогано Яка виглядає
and we see that our DCION Shake takes
і ми бачимо що наш dcion Shake займає
150 milliseconds,
150 мілісекунд
in fact, this is not additional to our year of
насправді це не додатково до нашого рік
Quest, because after  we
квесту тому що після того як ми
send from Kiev to Los Angeles
відправляємо від з Києва в лос-анджелес
our econology that Connection is all
наш екноволедж що Connection все
set up we can still we will
встановлений ми можемо ще ми все
receive everything we can start transmitting
отримаємо ми можемо почати передавати
data of our request without waiting for any
дані нашого запиту не дочікуючись ніякої
response so we will write 0 here i.e. we
відповіді тому ми тут напишемо 0 тобто
already have other numbers We already have 220
вже у нас інші цифри У нас вже 220
milliseconds That is it is 11 times more
мілісекунд Тобто це в 11 разів більше
than our backend processes these 20 m/s
ніж відпрацьовує наш бекенд оці 20 м/с
i.e. 220 instead of 20 but usually we have
тобто 220 замість 20 але зазвичай у нас
Not only
Не тільки
htp just which works on tcp we
htp просто який працює поtcp у нас
usually htps and htps also have tls henshake
зазвичай htps і htps теж є tls henshake
let's add the Shake body scheme
давайте додамо тілесхем Shake
and see what we will have a
і побачимо що у нас буде
body scheme we send some
тілесхеньшейк ми відправляємо якісь
Hello then some certificates are sent back to us
Hello потім назад нам відправляються
then we
якісь сертифікати потім ми
do a key exchange
робимо обмін ключами
and if
і якщо
in one direction and in the
в одну сторону і в
other direction our diagram is ready and this
другу сторону наша діаграмка готова і це
we have not yet taken into account that we have a DNS request
ми ще не врахували що у нас є DNS запит
yes in order to make a resolution to me in the
да для того щоб зробити різол до мене у
name we did not take into account such a thing as
імені ми не врахували таку штуку як
tissipi the word start because you cannot
тіссіпі слово старт тому що не можна
immediately start transmitting data at high
відразу почати передавати дані на великі
speeds there  if we have data for example
там швидкості якщо в нас даних наприклад
50 KB then we will still have those all the word
50 КБ то у нас ще вплине ті всі слово
start will be affected maybe we will analyze it next
старт можливо розберемо це Наступного
time But what we see here and now is a
разу Але що ми бачимо тут і зараз це
super ideal theoretical situation when here
супер ідеальна ситуація теоретична коли
Everything is super cool that is we have 150
от Все супер класно тобто в нас 150
milliseconds here the
мілісекунд тут
body henshake another 200 milliseconds let's go
тіло хеншейк ще 200 мілісекунд давайте
a little bit from the menu because Hello you can
трішечки з меню тому що Hello можна
send zero immediately and here we
відправляти нуль відразу а отут ми
can have to transmit encrypted
можемо маємо передавати шифрований
traffic so it will be 50 and we got
трафік тому буде 50 і у нас разом вийшло
420 milliseconds together Yes we have here 150 here
420 мілісекунд Да у нас є тут 150 тут
150 and here 120 together 420 mi seconds and this is
150 і тут 120 разом 420 мі секунд і це в
21 times more than how much
21 раз більше ніж то за скільки
our backend works so I think
відпрацьовує наш бекенд тому я думаю
many of you have heard about that there are
багато Хто із вас чув про те що такі є
things like cdn which allow us to place
штуки як cdn який дозволяють розмістити
our static files there images and so on
наші там статичні файли картинки і так
closer to the users so that they are
далі ближче до користувачів щоб вони
a little faster and in fact
трошечки швидше тягнулися і насправді
the question is not speed but in this delay
питання не швидкості а в цій затримці
so that there is less delay and so all these
щоб була менша затримка і тому оці всі
things like cdn are important but now look here
речі як cdn важливі але тепер дивіться
we have a cool  The diagram shows everything perfectly.
От у нас є класна діаграма все класно
These are super ideal conditions. Let's
показує Це супер ідеальні умови давайте
see how it is in practice. In order to
побачимо як воно на практиці і для того
do this, I made a small
щоб це зробити я зробив невеличкий
server. The
сервер
ip server shows that it is located in
ipшка показує що він знаходиться в
Los Angeles. I installed only
лос-анджелесі Я підняв на ньому тільки
Ingenex on it, nothing more and GTS. But
інженекс нічого більше і GTS але ми
now we will try to make a request and
зараз спробуємо зробити запит і
see what requests are going on the network.
подивитися які запити ходять по мережі
Using a tool like
використовуючи такою такій тул як
Voyensherk, you could use such and
воєншерк можна було використати такі
such. But in principle, you can
собі дам Але в принципі ви це все можете
repeat all this yourself at home. That is, you
повторити той самостійно вдома тобто
take the installation file,
берете встановлювати фаришак
run it and
запускаєте і
check. Look what I will do. I
перевіряєте Дивіться що я зроблю я
made a frog under the domain. The queen will die
зробив під домен жаба скріп маток здохне
for the test. Now I will try to make a
для тесту і Зараз я спробую зробити
request from the console to HTTP and check what VR
запит з консолі на htp і перевірити VR
Shark looks like. That is, we take our
Shark як це виглядає Тобто ми беремо наш
VR Shark, start recording
VR Shark починаємо запис
and now we make a request. We got
і тепер робимо запит це ми отримали
the answer. Let's see what we have. I will
відповідь давайте подивимось що у нас я
remove this filter. Look where we are. We will
приберу цей фільтр дивіться де нас Ми
ignore it. We will not
проігноруємо не будемо сьогодні його
analyze it today. I will make a separate video for the
аналізувати я зроблю окреме відео под
ENS. But here, if you quickly look around, we
єнс але тут якщо швидко оглянути ми
can see that we have a request for IP v4, a
можемо бачити що в нас є запит на IP v4
request for IPv6, and the same thing.  response but
запит на ipv6 і так само response але
we are primarily interested in this here request
нас цікавить в першу чергу цей вот запит
tcpe Hand Shake and this request Which
tcpe Hand Shake і цей запит Який тільки
we just did it was a defenseless tps in http
що ми зробили це був беззащит tps в http
and let's see what we have here that is
і давайте подивимось що у нас тут є
first we have hanshake I will change the
тобто перше у нас є hanshake я поміняю
display of
трішечки вигляд відображення
[music]
[музика]
time a little so that there are seconds From the previous
часу щоб були секунди Від попереднього
captured packet and we see that a
захопленого пакету і ми бачимо що був
packet with the flag seven was sent to the
відправлений пакет з флагом сім на
server and then the response came after
сервер а потім прийшла відповідь через
192 milliseconds 7ek then we
192 мілісекунди 7ek потім ми
send Ek
відправляємо Ек
almost immediately Yes because we do
практично відразу Да тому що ми нічого
n't wait for anything and immediately send our
не чекаємо і відразу відправляємо наш
http request and then we already get some
http запит і потім вже отримуємо якісь
responses that is let's see
відповіді тобто давайте подивимось
how much time it took us if we take it
скільки у нас зайняло часу якщо брати
from here to here We can see what it
звідси сюди Ми можемо бачити що у нас
took us without gtps this whole thing almost 400
зайняло без gtps ця вся штука майже 400
milliseconds so let's Now I will make an
мілісекунд так давайте Тепер я зроблю
htps request now I will be htps
htps запит от зараз мене буде htps
made the request stop and see what
зробили запит зупиняємо і дивимось що в
we got DNS we can ignore it
нас вийшло DNS можемо проігнорувати
actually works faster because it
він насправді відпрацьовує швидше тому
this request goes
що він цей запит іде
so far 192 168 51 that is to my
так далеко 192 168 51 тобто на мій
local router  and he somewhere there
локальний роутер і він десь там його
rakes it out or from the cache or goes to the
вигрібає або з киша або йде до
provider So it's not such a big
провайдера Тому це не така велика
problem And we can basically
проблема І ми можемо в принципі
see how much it took us everything about
подивитися скільки у нас зайняло все про
everything we have a year West response took from
все у нас рік Вест response зайняв від
880 milliseconds but let's look in
880 мілісекунд але давайте дивитися в
detail what we have first we see also
деталях що у нас є першими бачимо так
here this tcp shake Sin sinek-ek and we
само ось цей tcpеншейк Сін сінек-ек і ми
see that it took about 190
бачимо що він зайняв приблизно 190
milliseconds then how many there 71 milliseconds
мілісекунд потім скількись там 71 млседу
maple Hello That is we this is the difference between
клен Hello Тобто ми це різниця між
sent Ek and sent maple Hello
відправили Ек і відправили клен Hello
That is this is some internal our local
Тобто це якась внутрішня наша локальна
initialization to start this tls
ініціалізація щоб почати оцей tls
connection That is it is not related to the
з'єднання Тобто це не пов'язано з
network delay then
мережею затримкою далі
we receive Ek and we receive our from the
ми отримуємо Ек і отримуємо наш від
Hello server some information about the cipher
сервера Hello якусь інформацію про шифр
which to use and so on And it is already
який використовувати і так далі І це вже
190 milliseconds and basically further we see
190 мсекунд і в принципі далі ми бачимо
that went there ends this tils and
що пішли там закінчується цей tils і
then went to our application date In addition
потім пішли у нас application дата Крім
we see whether these are often ek-equati
того ми бачимо чи ці часто ек- екваті
that is periodically our client Well how do you
тобто періодично наш клієнт Ну як ти
work He has to confirm What
собі працюю Він має підтверджувати Що
He receives  data and this is the whole main
Він отримує дані і в цьому вся основна
idea because edp does not have this
ідея тому що edp немає цього
confirmation tcp has and we see that in
підтвердження tcp має і ми бачимо що на
practice our request Which theoretically should have been
практиці наш запит Який теоретично мав
processed in
відпрацьовувати за
420 milliseconds it processes twice as
420 мілісекунд він відпрацьовує ще два
long and practically there 800
рази довший і практично там 800
milliseconds and Let's check just
мілісекунд і Давайте перевіримо просто
Pink this server that is instead of http
Pink цього сервера тобто замість http
request We will just do a ping and see
запиту Ми зробимо просто пінг і побачимо
what comes out of it so we do a ping and we
що з цього вийде так ми робимо пінг і ми
see that ping there and back takes 192
бачимо що пінг туди і назад займає 192
seconds as we saw in Air Shark and this is me Of
секунди як ми бачили в Air Shark і це я
course Because we have wi-fi We have
Зрозуміло Тому що у нас є wi-fi У нас є
providers we have an indirect connection as we
провайдери у нас непрямий зв'язок як ми
would expect from point A to point B that is
би очікували з точки А в точку б тобто
today's practical ping is 190
практичний пінг сьогоднішній - це 190
milliseconds this is the first video in the series about
мілісекунд це перше відео із серії про
how the internet works so put a like
те як працює інтернет тому ставте лайк
write in the comments Do you want to
пишіть в коментарях Чи хочете
continue and that you would like to see in the
продовження і щоб хотіли побачити в
continuation And of course Subscribe
продовженні І звісно Підписуйтесь
share this video in chats there
поширюйте це відео в чатах там
forward to friends what will happen next further as of
пересилайте друзям що буде далі далі як
course I will tell you about DNS I will show How it works I will
звісно розповім про DNS покажу Як він
tell you about the reasons for tps in more detail  how is it
розповім про причиtps більш деталях як
going in general yes I promised to make a
відбувається взагалі є я обіцяв зробити
video about
відео про
asymmetric cryptography that's all it will be And I
асиметричну криптографію це все буде І я
think this will be a water video before
думаю це буде водне відео перед тим як
moving on to how tps works and as I
перейти до того як працюючи tps і як я
already said it's important to understand things how
вже казав важливий розбиратися в речах
they work that to be able to design
як вони працюють що вміти проектувати
correctly and understand the consequences of some
правильно і розуміти наслідки якихось
technical decisions and if you
там технічних рішень і якщо ви
are doing web development well understanding how the
займаєтесь веб-розробкою ну розуміти як
Internet works is very important so there will be a
працює Інтернет дуже важливо тому буде
whole series dedicated to how
ціла серія присвячена тому як працює
the Internet works
Інтернет